<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00069" xml:lang="de"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title><idno>65</idno>Karl Kaub an Familie Marx in London. Paris, Samstag, 17. März 1866</title></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition ana="#firstEdition">Dieser Brief wird hier erstmals veröffentlicht.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>IISG</institution>
                        <collection>Marx-Engels-Nachlass</collection>
                        <idno><idno type="shelfmark">D 2619/D V 44 Fotosign. 9577a–b</idno></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>Der Brief besteht aus einem Bogen dünnem, weißem Papier im Format
                            412&#160;×&#160;266&#160;mm. Kaub hat die erste und dritte Seite
                            vollständig beschrieben, die zweite und vierte Seite sind leer.
                            Schreibmaterial: schwarze Tinte. </p>
                        <p>Von unbekannter Hand: Nummerierung des Briefes: „2“ mit Bleistift auf der
                            ersten Seite oben in der Mitte; Vermerk mit schwarzer Tinte „Mars
                            17/66“, auf der vierten Seite unten rechts quer geschrieben.</p>
                        <p>Die Schreibweise wurde zurückhaltend korrigiert, die Eingriffe sind
                            ausgewiesen.</p>
                        <p>Kaub beantwortet, wie aus dem Brief zu ersehen, einen nicht überlieferten
                            Brief, vermutlich von Jenny Marx, geschrieben vor dem 17.&#160;März
                            1866.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                    <additional>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl>RGASPI f. 1 op. 5 d. 1646</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><correspDesc><correspAction type="sent"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460">Karl Kaub</persName><placeName>Paris</placeName><date when="1866-03-17"/></correspAction><correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="ed_cqm_n53_f1b">Marx, Familie (-)</persName><placeName>London</placeName></correspAction></correspDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2016-10-31T13:38:55Z</date> | <name>Regina Roth</name> | <orgName>Telota</orgName> | OxGarage DOCX to TEI | 2.15.0</change><change><date>2016-10-31T14:57:09+01:00</date> | <name>Sascha Grabsch</name> | <orgName>Telota</orgName> | convert_tei_file.py | 0.85</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="writingAct">
                <opener>
                    <dateline sameAs="MBDatumszeile"><pb/> Paris, Mars 17/1866</dateline>
                    <salute sameAs="MBAnrede">Dears, all of you</salute>
                </opener>
                <p sameAs="MBAdresse">33, Rue des trois Couronnes, du Temple</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextohneEinzug">It was surely the most brilliant idea, <seg type="comment"><orig>father Mohr</orig><note xml:id="aa963628-d326-455c-8f21-c15ff2906e86">Karl Marx.</note></seg>
                    ever had, when he got good <seg type="comment"><orig>Jenny</orig><note xml:id="d0c8e06f-a8ed-4233-9b1c-bcfbd75e6a1a"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003074">Jenny Marx (Tochter)</persName>.
                        </note></seg> to make me have those long expected and often thought of,
                    portraits. I now, without the slightest hesitation—boldly I say: you are the
                    most pathetical wordkeepers, this <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">wre<ex>t</ex>ched</expan> world has ever borne. Indeed, I was so
                    thoroughly pleased, when I saw your dear little heads dive out of <seg type="comment"><orig>your letter,</orig><note xml:id="ncbv_d43_1z">Der Brief
                            konnte nicht ermittelt werden.</note></seg> that—what do you think? that
                    I could not help heartily kissing them, without exception, and—niether of you
                    even plushed. Should however, any one of you feel vexed, at so much of a
                    stranger’s daring, there will be no other way, of taking revenge, at this my
                    criminal action, but to do the same to mine, if it should happen to be found
                    still in that rich collection, among the number of your friends; do it with as
                    angry looks as possibly you may—and never tell me of it&#160;(!)</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><seg type="comment"><orig>I was very deeply affected to
                            hear, that you had sickness and sorrow again reigning in your
                            house,</orig><note xml:id="a18ec1bc-c667-4d3d-8022-0b319689cb73">Seit
                            Ende Januar litt Marx an Furunkulose.</note></seg> and even more so as
                    you did have before. I know, that poor Mohr has not the time now to be ill and
                    keep his sheets. How much this very critical position, he of needs must have
                    found himself to be surprised by this new “fléau” in, must have contributed to
                    give you number of anxieties, I fully can appreciate. Mohr is, I often had
                    occasion to convince me of, by nature of an exellent disposition and of a most
                    brillant humour, as long as he is passably well, and able to smoke his pipe in
                    peace, but like the rest of us, being ill, he is likely to have his days, when
                    he gets awful out of time. If one, like him, has all his lifetime struggled and
                    made sail for one thing, has, with all his work and toil, at last reached close
                    his end—the land in sight, he drops his anchor—and finds his tackle short and
                    going back to sea again, he can not well help knitting his brows, and growing
                    damned wild. <seg type="comment"><orig>His work,</orig><note xml:id="dbd5ca04-8010-47cf-a156-415d55ff2bba">Gemeint ist hier Karl
                            Marx: Das Kapital; siehe <ref target="B00007/#a85fd331-e369-4613-bae5-8b4731d7edc3">Erl. zu Marx
                                an J. Ph. Becker, zwischen 9. und 15.1.1866.</ref>
                            <?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170517T122051+0200" comment="{{Erl. 6b}}."?>
                            <?oxy_comment_end?>(((lMarx,Karl:DasKapital.Bd.1.Hamburg1867)))</note></seg>
                    so eagerly expected by all his friends, that will have cost him so many nights
                    rests, and which, to my <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">beli<ex>e</ex>ve</expan>, in a great measure is the cause of his
                    continued ake and lingering health, by depriving him of all necessary rest and
                    distraction, I hope, as earnestly as one can hope, that is fully aware of its
                    importance, and bears his friendship streight at heart—will find its completion,
                    with natur’s resurrection—the all invigorating spring! I am convinced that this
                    weight, once off his mind, he will become another man, he will be merry as he
                    was before, and joy and happiness will enter streight at all your doors again.
                    If then, you careful keep the windows shut, you will find your rooms too small,
                    to hold it all, and Mohr will be obliged to take the sails and come over to me,
                    to Paris, and spend a happy month with me. If my rustic habitation, will then be
                    good enough, he shall be heartily welcome.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">We had a most wretched winter here. The weather was as
                    changeable and <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">unhea<ex>l</ex>thy</expan> as ever I had seen in London. Raining, hot and
                    cold were dayly changing twice and more than twice. The number of ills is
                    greater as ever has been seen before, the hospitals are crowded and burrial
                    undertaking is the best business out. Combined with that, things have been
                    generally very dull here, and living has attained a higher price, as I knew it
                    to have been at London, at the time I left.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">I for my own part, have still kept very well, and the
                    numberless complaints, I was subjected to, in foggy London, are all gone by. I
                    think if I had stood another year or two on Englands smoky shores, I should have
                    kicked the bucket like a man. I think one ought not to do so any sooner than he
                    can help. </p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><pb/> Our business goes on now, as well as can be
                    expected under such unfavorable circumstances, as than we had had to begin in.
                    We have plenty of work, even so much, that we are almost smothered with it. The
                    only great misfortune in the matter is, that we have not sufficiently <hi rendition="#u">tin</hi> to make it go and role, and make it worth our’s
                    while. As things are now, we have about 35 or 40,000&#160;Fr. in the concern. If
                    we wanted to go on, any way favourably, we ought now at least to have another
                    800 or 1000&#160;<unclear reason="covered" cert="high">£</unclear> to put in to
                    it. As it were, we are dependent of a multitude of unfavourable circumstances,
                    of different individuals etc. we might all free ourselfs without delay. There
                    has been offerd to us, for example, the execution of <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high">censoring</unclear> the whole materials of a large manufactury—a
                    work amounting to more than 100,000&#160;Fr. There might be 25,000&#160;Fr. got
                    out of it in considerably less than a year, and the work we have, carried on at
                    the same time. But as we are <hi rendition="#u">almost</hi> pennyless—the whole
                    of what little we have, all laid out, and not by far enough—there is not to be
                    thought of such an undertaking, the job will pass our noses clean, although the
                    preference would have been given to us, had we been able to execute it without
                    the help of any one. It will fall to the lot of one that has got tin enough.
                    However I do not complain, as I know it would be of no use. <seg type="comment"><orig>Rothchild, they say, was once on <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">bo<ex>a</ex>rd</expan> of one of the
                            Rhin-steamers, when a pickpocket tried to rob the poor Baron. His
                            friend, who stood by, seeing it, laid hand on the fellow, and wanted, to
                            have him locked up. “Never mind” said Rothchild “let the chap loose, we
                            too have begun in so small a way.”</orig><note xml:id="df5763ce-222b-4ee7-9748-b5a24bfb43ff">Es handelt sich um eine
                            bekannte Anekdote. Gemeint sind hier vermutlich, auch wegen des im Brief
                            genannten österreichischen Militärs <persName key="ed_kvh_jmc_3y">Ludwig
                                Freiherr von Gablenz</persName>, die <persName key="ed_lg3_rnt_zy">Wiener Rothschilds</persName>, somit entweder <persName key="ed_vzg_hpt_zy">Anselm Salomon Freiherr von
                                Rothschild</persName> oder noch sein Vater, <persName key="ed_gyf_npt_zy">Salomon Meyer Freiherr von
                            Rothschild</persName>. </note></seg>—So so. We are but little thiefs
                    now, and will have a damned hard pull to get on, but if we but have a little
                    chance—we may. There is no possibility of getting out of it now! We either must
                    swimm or drown. The only thing, that grieves me much, is, that before we get out
                    of the deepest mud—if out we get at all—those few good years, I have still
                    before me, will have gone by, and things which might have been done perhaps even
                    now, although it is already late, will be to late for ever.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">To another picture!<persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460"> I</persName> dare not neglect, my dear Marx,
                    to tell you of a thing which might perhaps at a very early period, enter so
                    extensivly into the composure of our present society, that this our society
                    would cease to resemble itself. The period of steam will be at its end. A
                    Frenchman, of the name of <persName key="ed_xg4_3rr_3z">Rebour</persName>, and
                    whose <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">acqu<ex>a</ex>inta</expan><ex>n</ex>ce I had the pleasure of making, has
                    lately modified an invention, he has already tried before a numerous public of
                        <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">s<ex>c</ex>ientific</expan>
                    men in 1853, in Russia, Amerika and lastly in England, which will be able of
                    propounding any railway train or doing any kind of work, steam engines are doing
                    now, without any power, but its <hi rendition="#u">own weight</hi> as a moteur.
                    Do not think I am out of mind. In 53 already, the future consequences of such an
                    invention have been so thoroughly understood in London, at a Banquet given to
                        M.&#160;<persName key="ed_xg4_3rr_3z">Rebour</persName> at
                    Sablonnière-Hôtel, Leicester Square, that high placed men thought wise to poison
                    the man, which they affected by presenting him a slize of cake, where a laurel
                    &amp; a rose were laid on. However he survived. To day, he is associated with
                        <seg type="comment"><orig>Baron <persName key="ed_vzg_hpt_zy">Rothchild</persName></orig><note xml:id="d673a754-6df7-46e3-b1f0-596348c71ae6"><persName key="ed_vzg_hpt_zy">Anselm Salomon Freiherr von
                                Rothschild</persName>.</note></seg>, General von <persName key="ed_kvh_jmc_3y">Gablenz</persName> and the devil knows who all. The
                    enormous capital has been voted, and in a few months his waggon will go from
                    Paris to Marseille and back at a rate of 40&#160;miles an hour, without steam or
                    any other motive power but the <hi rendition="#u">waggons own weight</hi>. His
                    invention applicated on the fly-wheel of an ordinary steam engine, gives 80%
                    economy in power. A steam engine of 4&#160;<expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">hors<ex>e</ex></expan> for example, he can make by
                    an application of his invention to make 20&#160;<expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">hors<ex>e</ex></expan> without a pennyworth more
                    coals. However this is nothing, as the steamengines will be done away with all
                    together. Up to now: augmentation of weight, was <hi rendition="#u">augmentation</hi> of friction. He upsets all and prooves, in spite of all
                    the proud Chorophees of Knowledge that, if things are in the right condition:
                    augmentation of weight is impossible without <hi rendition="#u">diminution</hi>
                    of friction. This is the great basis on which his invention reposes. The good
                    man has great difficulties to fight with. He finds bad will every where. A thing
                    which must cause such an enormous “deplacement de richesse” is not likely to
                    find many friend. I could write much more about it. If you will <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">beli<ex>e</ex>ve</expan> me, that I
                    am not out of mind, and you feel interested in it, I shall write more about the
                    progress of it. I consider the man a great genius, and those that will lend
                    hands to bring it to life, as very useful members of society. He finds the
                    greatest opposition in the “haute bourgeoisie”. <seg type="comment"><orig><anchor type="verweisziel" xml:id="start_t4y_3mv_4z"/>The
                            same M. <persName key="ed_xg4_3rr_3z">Rebour</persName>, assures me—but
                            the matter shall not yet be talked of, as he has since the London
                            affairs some reason to be careful—that he is able to separate hydrogene
                            from oxigene in a way that costs 2&#160;sous par jour for a fire to melt
                            iron with. I think the man to be of also sound mind, honest and very
                            intelligent as much as I know now of him.<anchor type="verweisziel" xml:id="stop_t4y_3mv_4z"/></orig><note xml:id="f2131023-2adf-4093-b536-7e8770377ae0">Diese Stelle erwähnt <ref target="B00082/#start_fmt_sjf_4z">Marx im Brief an Engels vom
                                2.&#160;April 1866</ref>
                            <?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170413T113231+0200" comment="({{Br. 79.72–77}})"?>.<?oxy_comment_end?></note></seg>
                    I think in such a baffling case as this, this testimonial is not <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">superfl<ex>u</ex>ous</expan>. I may
                    be wrong, as so many mortals have been wrong before, but I doubt it strongly. I
                    am not entousiaste. I pray you—dont <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">beli<ex>e</ex>ve</expan> a word of all that, I
                    dont like people that <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">beli<ex>e</ex>ve</expan> before they see and <hi rendition="#u">understand.</hi> Let me hear soon something of you.</p>
                <closer sameAs="MBUnterschrift"><!--<hi rend="color(0000FF)">{u2}</hi>-->My earnest love to
                    all of you.<lb/>Ch. Kaub </closer>
            </div></body></text></TEI>