<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00092" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title><idno>89</idno>Wilhelm Liebknecht an Karl Marx in London. Leipzig, Samstag,
                    14. April 1866</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition ana="#firstEdition">Dieser Brief wird hier erstmals
                    veröffentlicht.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>RGASPI</institution>
                        <idno><idno type="shelfmark">f. 21 op. 1 d. 188/2</idno></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>Der Brief besteht aus einem Bogen mittelstarkem, weißem Papier im Format
                            285&#160;×&#160;224&#160;mm. Liebknecht hat alle vier Seiten vollständig
                            beschrieben, die letzte Passage steht auf der ersten Seite oben links.
                            Schreibmaterial: schwarze Tinte.</p>
                        <p>Die Jahresangabe 1866 stützt sich auf die Tatsache, dass Liebknecht hier
                            offensichtlich Marx' Brief vom 6.&#160;April 1866 (Marx an W.
                            Liebknecht, 6.4.1866) beantwortet.</p>
                        <p>Die Beilage („... encloses a letter.“) ist nicht überliefert. Siehe
                            Erl.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002822">Wilhelm Liebknecht</persName>
                    <placeName>Leipzig</placeName>
                    <date when="1866-04-14"/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName>
                    <placeName>London</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2016-10-31T13:39:10Z</date> | <name>Regina Roth</name> |
                        <orgName>Telota</orgName> | OxGarage DOCX to TEI | 2.15.0</change>
                <change><date>2016-10-31T14:57:09+01:00</date> | <name>Sascha Grabsch</name> |
                        <orgName>Telota</orgName> | convert_tei_file.py | 0.85</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="writingAct">
                <opener><dateline sameAs="MBDatumszeile"><pb/> 10 Bayrische
                        Str.<lb/>Leipzig.<lb/>Apr. 14, 65.</dateline><salute sameAs="MBAnrede">Dear
                        Williams!</salute></opener>
                <p sameAs="MBTextohneEinzug">So you are all right again. Well, you had given us a
                    tremendous fright; I really thought you had resolved on doing your enemies the
                    only kindness, they have ever to expect from you, viz removing from this vale of
                    sorrow.—</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">By the bye, <hi rendition="#u">mind </hi><seg type="comment"><orig><hi rendition="#u">what </hi><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002616"><expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline"><hi rendition="#u">Kugelm<ex>ann</ex></hi></expan></persName><hi rendition="#u"> wrote you</hi></orig><note xml:id="b7580e42-860c-4abb-859f-f9adf63c5329">Siehe <ref target="B00079">L. Kugelmann an Marx,
                                30.3.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170320T165754+0100" comment="{{Br. 76}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref>.</note></seg><hi rendition="#u"> in his professional capacity</hi>. He is an <hi rendition="#u">excellent</hi> physician.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Now about the Int. A. <seg type="comment"><orig>The six
                            cards</orig><note xml:id="ecc43d9e-caf6-4faf-b25c-45d27eadbd3c">
                            International Working Men’s Association. Member’s Annual Subscription
                            Card [for 1866]. [London 1865]. (((lInternational Working Men’s
                            Association. Member’s Annual Subscription Card [for 1866]. [London
                            1865]))) Marx übersandte die Mitgliedskarten der IAA an Liebknecht mit
                            seinem Brief vom 15.&#160;Januar 1866. Siehe <ref target="B00011/#start_jml_clq_pz">Marx an W. Liebknecht,
                                15.1.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170418T135001+0200" comment="{{Br. 10.17–25}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref>
                            und <ref target="B00011/#cb864592-8d8a-4a93-b073-8383b8d607bc">Erl. zu
                                Marx an W. Liebknecht,
                            15.1.1866.</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T112550+0200" comment="{{Erl._10c}}."?></note><?oxy_comment_end?></seg>
                    are disposed of; for three I have not yet got the money; that for the other
                    three I should send you now, if I had the amount ready. (you will get the
                        2&#160;<expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">r<ex>eichstaler</ex></expan> with one of my next letters). The misfortune
                    is, I am so overwhelmed with work (business-, domestic etc.) that I cannot well
                    attend to those small matters, else I might have squeezed all the money out and
                    disposed of many more cards. However I should like some more, as I have several
                    people willing to join. The members here are all more or less influential men.
                    In a short time I hope to have regular <hi rendition="#u">assistance</hi> and
                    then better <hi rendition="#u">outward</hi> results will be shown. I say
                    “outward”—for in <hi rendition="#u">reality</hi> things have progressed better,
                    than could be expected. The workingmen of this town (and the <hi rendition="#u">same</hi> holds good for a great part of Germany); but yesterday the
                    unthinking tools (and fools) of the “liberal” middle class, are now fighting
                    under their own banner; of course there is much to be desired yet, still the
                    separation of classes is taking place, the old fusion and confusion (<persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000004342">Schulze's</persName> “Urbrei”) rapidly giving
                    way to a clearer view of men and things. <pb/> I am accused of having thrown the
                    torch of discord in this “democratic” fools' paradise called Leipzig, where the
                    workmen-wolves were grazing peacefully and “kemiedlig” (guess what it means) at
                    the side of the capitalist-lambs “democrats” good and true all of them. Query?
                    Who are the wolves and who the lambs? <seg type="comment"><orig>Omne simile
                            claudicat.</orig><note xml:id="c2566801-32d2-46b9-947a-af802042121d">Jedes Gleichnis hinkt (lat.).</note></seg>) Unfortunately the pious
                    scoundrels, whose bile I have stirred up, put something of a <hi rendition="#u">denunciatory</hi> character into their attacks, and I must take great care,
                    if I want to avoid <seg type="comment"><orig>a repetition of my last Berlin
                            experience.</orig><note xml:id="b0e31f5c-ddba-4f4a-8af4-294f0ae081ce">Zur Ausweisung Liebknechts aus Berlin siehe <ref target="B00011/#a4016170-75c2-4918-b14f-5981f8456429">Erl. zu Marx
                                an W. Liebknecht,
                            15.1.1866.</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T112929+0200" comment="{{Erl. 10e}}."?></note><?oxy_comment_end?></seg>
                    In spite of the hatred these “Saechser” wear to <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000441">Bismarck</persName>, they would take the
                    slightest hint of his police, to send me into some other Deutsches Vaterland.
                    And especially now they are so terribly afraid of the Pickelhauben.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Now I come to the principal drawback of the I.&#160;A.
                    movement in Germany—<seg type="comment"><orig>the necessity of confining
                            ourselves to individual memberships. The “Vereinsgesetze” have lately
                            been carried out with <hi rendition="#u">great</hi> severity and
                            strictness;</orig><note xml:id="e55778cd-6b21-4a1e-8ec4-f581fbec95e0">Siehe <ref target="B00019/#be344359-52ce-4f90-9a9f-630c0da8624f">Erl.
                                zu W. Liebknecht an Marx,
                            21.1.1866.</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T113453+0200" comment="{{Erl. 18c}}."?></note><?oxy_comment_end?></seg>
                    here in Saxony the “Arbeiterbildungsvereine” were offered (a few months ago) the
                    “favour” of being allowed to form so called “Gauverbände”, that is, to establish
                    a common organisation and correspondence; but to the “favour” the condition was
                    added, that the societies should not have to meddle with politics, social
                    questions etc. The delegates assembled to examine the “present” had sense and
                    honour enough to decline the gift; but the consequence was that all the
                    “Vereine” have since been put under a pretty close control. Under these
                    circumstances it is quite impossible <pb/> to found public sections of the
                    I.&#160;A., and to make any considerable Propaganda under its <hi rendition="#u">firm.</hi> I have lectured about it, everybody is for it, but people don't
                    see of what <hi rendition="#u">practical</hi> use it is, to join a society, that
                    for them only exists as an ungraspable “idea”. The only way, to make practical
                        <hi rendition="#u">direct</hi> propaganda for the I.&#160;A. would be the
                    establishment of a German Press organ, <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000317">Becker's</persName>
                    <bibl sameAs="zzDer Vorbote">Vorbote</bibl> not being what is wanted. However, I
                    won't dream of such things. Of course, I shall be able, or rather <hi rendition="#u">we</hi> shall be able to collect a small knot of workmen
                    round the I.&#160;A.&#160;Banner, but on the whole I must confine myself to work
                    for the <hi rendition="#u">principles</hi>; and that I have done successfully
                    until now. I <hi rendition="#u">must</hi> use the existing societies, and before
                    long I hope to have a great many of them at our disposition.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Oh! if we but had a review or a weekly paper, however
                    small! And, as this cannot be, if it were but possible that, <hi rendition="#u">besides</hi>
                    <seg type="comment"><orig>your Economy,</orig><note xml:id="a53c10d2-6eda-436e-9f8b-487d35210f8e">Gemeint ist hier Karl
                            Marx: Das Kapital; siehe <ref target="B00007/#a85fd331-e369-4613-bae5-8b4731d7edc3">Erl. zu Marx
                                an J. Ph. Becker, zwischen 9. und 15.1.1866.</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T113719+0200" comment="{{Erl. 6b}}."?>
                            <?oxy_comment_end?>(((lMarx,Karl:DasKapital.Bd.1.Hamburg1867)))</note></seg>
                    some smaller works could be republished, before all <seg type="comment"><orig><hi rendition="#u">Engels</hi>' Lage der arbeitenden
                            etc.</orig><note xml:id="d6938e5f-6cd9-4a5f-9683-92a7e45f81c3">Friedrich
                            Engels: Die Lage der arbeitenden Klasse in England. Nach eigner
                            Anschauung und authentischen Quellen. Leipzig 1845.
                            (((lEngels,Friedrich:Die_Lage der arbeitenden Klasse in England. Leipzig
                            1845))) Liebknecht hatte schon mehrfach die Notwendigkeit angesprochen,
                            diese Arbeit neu herauszugeben. Siehe, z.B. MEGA²&#160;III/13.
                            Br.&#160;200.61–64, Br._210.59–61, Br._221.5–7, Br._260.26–27,
                            Br._299.8–9 und Br._336.21–23. Siehe auch <ref target="B00036/#nv2g_cfy_5y">Erl. zu Marx an Engels,
                                10.2.1866.</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T130244+0200" comment="{{Erl. 33d}}."?></note><?oxy_comment_end?></seg>
                    in a new Edition. That would be a splendid auxiliary to your work, something
                    like a practical <seg type="comment"><orig>demonstratio ad oculos.</orig><note xml:id="f0343b72-b3dd-4301-8ff2-32ab89e49fb8">Beweis durch Augenschein
                            (lat.).</note></seg></p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><anchor type="verweisziel" xml:id="start_wqg_zxw_mz"/>I
                    told you already,—and you must neither forget nor neglect it—that I am on good
                    terms with <seg type="comment"><orig>the South- and Middle german
                            “Volkspartei”,</orig><note xml:id="nd2k_cfp_dz">Die Demokratische
                            Volkspartei (1863–1866).</note></seg> that their organ, <seg type="comment"><orig><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001300">Eckard's</persName> “Deutsches <bibl sameAs="zzDeutsches Wochenblatt">Wochenblatt”</bibl></orig><note xml:id="nktz_pfp_dz">Zum „Deutschen Wochenblatt“ siehe auch Georg
                            Eckert: Das „Deutsche Wochenblatt“ und die Internationale
                            Arbeiter-Assoziation. In: Archiv für Sozialgeschichte. Bd.&#160;4.
                            Hannover 1964. S.&#160;579–598. (((lEckert,Georg:_Das „Deutsche
                            Wochenblatt“ und die Internationale Arbeiter-Assoziation. In: Archiv für
                            Sozialgeschichte. Bd.&#160;4. Hannover 1964.
                        S.&#160;579–598)))</note></seg>
                    <seg type="comment"><orig>is unreservedly at our service,</orig><note xml:id="nhl1_kgp_dz">Siehe <ref target="B00016/#start_udy_llq_pz">W.
                                Liebknecht an Marx,
                                18.1.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170418T135244+0200" comment="{{Br. 15.46-48}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref>
                            und <ref target="B00016/#e418f926-2f84-48cf-8833-4dfe162019c0">Erl. zu
                                W. Liebknecht an Marx, 18.1.1866</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T130653+0200" comment="{{Erl. _15n}} "?>
                            <?oxy_comment_end?>und <ref target="B00016/#nqvl_jws_gy">Erl. zu W.
                                Liebknecht an Marx,
                            18.1.1866.</ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T130802+0200" comment="{{15p}}."?></note><?oxy_comment_end?></seg>
                    and that I have some other papers, that will take anything coming from us.
                        <anchor type="verweisziel" xml:id="stop_wqg_zxw_mz"/></p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><pb/> See, that notices announcing the appearance of the
                    Economy are printed, and published in time; and as soon as the work is out,
                    Engels ought to write a Review&#160;...</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">You will have perceived that our <seg type="comment"><orig>Fortschrittler</orig><note xml:id="f2c48adb-68f5-4e55-a334-c67ab32c6107">Mitglieder der Deutschen
                            Fortschrittspartei (1861-1884).</note></seg> are preparing to turn
                        <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000441">Bismarck's</persName> Parliament
                    into a pretext, to run over to him. If he got <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003392">Bonaparte's</persName> help for a war against
                    Austria, or rather if he was allowed to join (as an active or passive ally)
                    Bonaparte in a war against Austria, the whole Fortschrittsparty would be
                    Bonaparto-Bismarckisch. But I don't think Bonaparte will get out of <seg type="comment"><orig>his <hi rendition="#u">Mexican</hi>
                        scrape</orig><note xml:id="f55b9843-4684-4d80-938c-88434bcb888e">Die französische
                            Intervention in Mexiko 1861-1867.</note></seg> in time, for that last
                    convention is only a miserable humbug.—As a reminiscence of the late War panic I
                    will yet tell you, that I <hi rendition="#u">never</hi> witnessed a more
                    wretched spectacle than those “liberal” (even “democratic”) Philisters cowering
                    down like a flock of sheep, and with eyes shut waiting for the blow to fall down
                    on their posteriors. And we “the nation of thinkers”! <seg type="comment"><orig>Lucus a non lucendo.</orig><note xml:id="ed372dcf-ed45-49ff-9e35-50be223855ad">Sprichwörtlich (lat.) für
                            die Bezeichnung einer falschen Etymologie, die Herleitung eines Wortes
                            aus seinem Gegenteil – Der Hain wird lucus genannt, weil es darin nicht
                            hell ist (non lucet). Nach Marcus Fabius Quintilianus: De institutione
                            oratoria. I, 6, 34. (((lQuintilianus:De_institutione oratoria)))
                        </note></seg></p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Apropos German affairs are now rather interesting, would
                    it not be possible for the “<bibl sameAs="zzThe Commonwealth">Commonwealth”</bibl> to take (and <hi rendition="#u">pay</hi> moderately) a
                    weekly letter from Germany? I am really at my wit's end; all my papers pay badly
                    and irregularly, and those constant money-cares make me half ill. I have about
                        500&#160;<expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">r<ex>eichstaler</ex></expan> a year <hi rendition="#u">certain</hi>, and
                    want about two hundred more—by God a modest wish!—then I might manage to <hi rendition="#u">live</hi>—and to <hi rendition="#u">work</hi> ten times
                    better than at present. You must know, that <hi rendition="#u">all</hi> German
                    papers, that pay well, either belong to the “Reaction” or to the
                    “Fortschrittler” and so I am sitting between two chairs. It is true, <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002471">Keil</persName>, <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000618">Brockhaus</persName>
                    etc. asked me to write for them, but somehow I found it impossible.</p>
                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Good bye. Write soon; mind your health; my love to all.
                        <seg type="comment"><orig>My <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002819">wife</persName>
                            encloses a letter.</orig><note xml:id="a9271e91-1c17-44dd-87e2-06b3d171d56e">Der Brief von <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002819">Ernestine Liebknecht</persName>,
                            vermutlich an <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003075">Jenny
                                Marx</persName> und geschrieben spätestens am 14.&#160;April 1866,
                            konnte nicht ermittelt werden.</note></seg></p>
                <closer sameAs="MBUnterschrift">Yours truly<lb/>J. Miller. </closer>
                <p>/ Dont' forget to send the papers regularly.— I am a Pechvogel; <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000011735">Weiss</persName> has been forced out of <seg type="comment"><orig>the Berlin “Reform”</orig><note xml:id="b0dd3ba5-e7b5-4436-b924-9eec021d4e2c">„Berliner Reform“.
                            (((zBerliner_Reform)))
                        </note></seg><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?><index indexName="XE">
                        <term>zzBerliner Reform</term>
                    </index><?oxy_custom_end?> and <seg type="comment"><persName key="ed_nfr_bbv_hz"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003178"><orig>Toby</orig></persName></persName><note xml:id="nerq_kjp_dz">Hund aus dem traditionellen englischen Puppenspiel „Punch and Judy“,
                            das dem deutschen Kaspertheater ähnlich ist. Von Marx, Engels und ihren
                            Freunden wurde Toby als Spottname für <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003178">Eduard Meyen</persName> benutzt. Der
                            demokatische Journalist Eduard Meyen, der im Hamburger „Freischütz“
                            (((z))) für <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000004961">Karl Vogt</persName>
                            Patei ergriffen hatte, war von Marx in seiner Streitschrift „Herr Vogt“
                            mit dem Hund Toby auf dem Titelblatt des humoristischen Wochenblatts
                            „Punch, or the London Charivari“ (((z))) verglichen worden (siehe
                            MEGA²&#160;I/18. S.253.4–255.40).</note></seg> has wormed himself in
                    again. W. had just invited me, to write for the paper!— /</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>