<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00101" xml:lang="de">
        <teiHeader>
                <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                                <title><idno>97</idno>Karl Kaub an Familie Marx in London. Paris,
                                        Dienstag, 1. Mai 1866</title>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                                <edition ana="#firstEdition">Dieser Brief wird hier erstmals
                                        veröffentlicht.</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                                <p>unknown</p>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                                <msDesc>
                                        <msIdentifier>
                                                <institution>IISG</institution>
                                                <collection>Marx-Engels-Nachlass</collection>
                                                <idno><idno type="shelfmark">D 2620/D V 45.
                                                  Fotosign. 9580a–b bzw. 9579</idno></idno>
                                        </msIdentifier>
                                        <physDesc>
                                                <p>Der Brief besteht aus einem Bogen und einem Blatt
                                                  dünnem, weißem Papier im Format
                                                  412&#160;×&#160;266&#160;mm bzw.
                                                  207&#160;×&#160;266&#160;mm. Die erste, dritte und
                                                  fünfte Seite hat Kaub vollständig beschrieben, die
                                                  zweite, vierte und sechste sind leer. Die fünfte
                                                  Seite hat Kaub mit „III“ paginiert.
                                                  Schreibmaterial: schwarze Tinte.</p>
                                                <p>Vermutlich von Marx’ Hand: Anstreichungen mit
                                                  schwarzer Tinte auf der ersten und dritten Seite
                                                  („Our international“  bis „men“ und „Creamer“ bis
                                                  „ways“).</p>
                                                <p>Von unbekannter Hand: Vermerk „Mai i. 66“ mit
                                                  schwarzer Tinte auf der vierten Seite unten am
                                                  rechten Rand quer. </p>
                                                <p>Kaub hat den Brief versehentlich mit „Sunday“
                                                  datiert, während der 1.&#160;Mai 1866 auf einen
                                                  Dienstag fällt.</p>
                                                <p>In die Schreibweise Kaubs wurde behutsam, allein
                                                  dem Textverständnis dienend, eingegriffen.
                                                  Sämtliche Eingriffe sind ausgewiesen. </p>
                                        </physDesc>
                                        <additional>
                                                <listBibl>
                                                  <bibl>RGASPI f. 1 op. 1 d. 5588</bibl>
                                                </listBibl>
                                        </additional>
                                </msDesc>
                        </sourceDesc>
                </fileDesc>
                <profileDesc>
                        <correspDesc>
                                <correspAction type="sent">
                                        <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460">Karl Kaub</persName>
                                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                                        <date when="1866-05-01"/>
                                </correspAction>
                                <correspAction type="received">
                                        <persName key="ed_cqm_n53_f1b">Marx, Familie (-)</persName>
                                        <placeName>London</placeName>
                                </correspAction>
                        </correspDesc>
                </profileDesc>
                <revisionDesc>
                        <listChange>
                                <change><date>2016-10-31T13:39:15Z</date> | <name>Regina Roth</name>
                                        | <orgName>Telota</orgName> | OxGarage DOCX to TEI |
                                        2.15.0</change>
                                <change><date>2016-10-31T14:57:10+01:00</date> | <name>Sascha
                                                Grabsch</name> | <orgName>Telota</orgName> |
                                        convert_tei_file.py | 0.85</change>
                        </listChange>
                </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
                <body>
                        <div type="writingAct">
                                <opener>
                                        <p sameAs="MBAdresse"><pb/> 33, Rue des trois Couronnes, du
                                                Temple</p>
                                        <dateline sameAs="MBDatumszeile">Paris Mai 1/1866<lb/>Sunday
                                                afternoon.</dateline>
                                        <salute sameAs="MBAnrede">My dear friends,</salute>
                                </opener>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextohneEinzug">Mohr must be made of a goodish bit of
                                        stuff.—Tossed about, for half a lifetime, as he has been,
                                        from wave to shore, from shore to wave—but wretched little
                                        amusement and far to much hard work—to this, to have been
                                        badly afflicted for something like a tenth part of a
                                        century, by continued sickness, and yet to hold his head up
                                        and walk again, like a man&#160;… this seems more than one
                                        can do, without the aid of magic powers. But there are
                                        occasions, at which men seem much alike—if looked at from a
                                        goodly distance. For example we all are always ready to
                                                <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">beli<ex>e</ex>ve</expan> any thing, however
                                        improbable it may seem, if it only chances to fit our
                                        likeings. I tell you, it fits mine—and I should like to see
                                        you well. I was exceedingly pleased to hear you are out of
                                        all danger now and even better, as you ever was before. So
                                        told me <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000004249">Schily</persName> at least, who had some
                                        correspondence from <seg type="comment"><orig>Rhinländer</orig><note xml:id="d9dac5e3-e77a-456b-881b-4f9a6aa24885"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003961">Georg
                                                  Friedrich Rheinlaender</persName>. </note></seg>—I
                                        belive.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">If you but could do as you liked, it
                                        would be infinitly better for you to live altogether
                                        somewhere on the sea side, or in some other merry place,
                                        than in that nasty London. It will never do for any one that
                                        once had serious wreck of health. Besides this, there is, in
                                        such an accumulation, to much cause for you, to meet with
                                        anger and annoyance … Come on, I shall talk to you now, like
                                        an old man. But don't laugh.—In my high opinion, there is,
                                        in every man's life, a decided period, when he rejoices to
                                        study and to learn, whatever it will cost him; learn more
                                        and more, and all he meets, he takes to heart, as so much of
                                        a useful lesson.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">There comes then, inevitably too—another
                                        period, when he gets sick of any further learning and often
                                        even, should like to know of many things, far less. He now
                                        rejoices in forgetting. Theese two periods are however
                                        seldom sharply trenched, but to the contrary, so closely
                                        often interweaven, at the ends and beginning of each of
                                        them, that most poeples are not aware of an existing change,
                                        even if it existes for years and years. Some catastrophe
                                        than, in their life, that does come on like a thunderstorm
                                        in spring, does set them suddenly on the alarm—they percieve
                                        the accomplished change, they think the effect to be the
                                        cause, belive the world to have grown worse, of what it ever
                                        was before—grow dull and never smile, as on the eve, the day
                                        of which they lay their heads on chaps … I do belive, that
                                        my good Mohr is one of those, who, by the life they had to
                                        lead, must long have reached the highest pitch in studying
                                        mankind. His philosophy must be formed. He needs no more to
                                        know, and would do well, if he could but forget. He must
                                        have passed his learning phase, when he thought, that every
                                        new deception he was subjected to, that every <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">fals<ex>e</ex></expan> friend he brake with, was
                                        worthy lesson for a future time, and he would profit of.
                                        No—them self same lessons, in the present day, will make one
                                        heartsick and spoil the blood. And crowded London is sure
                                        not a place, where one could soon forget, what he has seen
                                        there most. One wants a merry land for this, a deep blue
                                        sea—a lovely shore, the jolly boulevards, et du petit bleu.
                                        But all this wanting, you have dull hours, the physik-battle
                                        takes the place of books and the pipe, you do not enjoy your
                                        life by half, and almost wish that you should be no more. I
                                        have felt all this as well, and therefore feel with each
                                        one, that does feel like I.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Our international, I fear, was not much
                                        either, as a sweet deception. What you have told me in <seg type="comment"><orig>your letter,</orig><note xml:id="e76c508b-af25-476f-827a-81e831d482d9">Der
                                                  Brief von Marx’ (bzw. vermutlich Jenny Marx) an
                                                  <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460">Kaub</persName>, geschrieben zwischen
                                                  17.&#160;März (siehe Br.&#160;65) und 1.&#160;Mai
                                                  1866, ist nicht überliefert.</note></seg> I never
                                        should have dared to belive. It must have much affected you.
                                        It did not much affect me, as I am still a little in my
                                        learning mood, and think of taking it <seg type="comment"><orig>ad notam.</orig><note xml:id="ee8a3b82-ef30-42fd-9958-34037c143624">zur
                                                  Kenntnis (lat.).</note></seg> Some more of these
                                        events, and with same effect, I think, I will be able as
                                        well, to kick myself out of this phase. <seg type="comment"><orig><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001027">Creamer</persName>,</orig><note xml:id="b24e5544-affb-4d9e-9ebe-e55ff8102ece"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001027">William
                                                  Randall Cremer</persName>. </note></seg>
                                        <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003494">Odgers</persName>,
                                                <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002244">Howel</persName>, all these immolating,
                                        selfdeneying, generous, intelligent and I know not what
                                        all—creatures, that looked so streight at each man's face,
                                        and were so bold, because they said: they know they were in
                                        truth—I see—they showd no better than the rest of men. </p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><pb/> They wagg'd their tale as long as
                                        they smelled crap, that seemed quite close at hand. I for my
                                        part, I dare not exactly blame any one, that does things out
                                        of interest. But one thing I hate—and this is, if poeple do
                                        it in to showy and to unclean a manner. Do nothing without
                                        an interest, but at least hide it, and do it in a decent
                                        manner. To look for interest, I think, is so general and
                                        natural a disposition, that you will find it to be the
                                        motive power for all and every one, from the meanest animal,
                                        through mankind, the saints all and the angels, together
                                        with our good old man in heaven. As to him, we are told, he
                                        lived a huge tremendous part of his eternity, in stern
                                        lazyness and annoyance, until at last he grew so dammnedably
                                        sick and tired of it, nothing but gaping and scratching his
                                        head, that he made up his mind to put a step to it—and made
                                        the world. His interest then was, to get some sport—need man
                                        to be ashamed? In fact; motive, reason, interest, are all
                                        but different words for the very selfsame thing. A man gives
                                        a poor beggar a “bob” he sais; he followd the generous
                                        motive of doing good to others. This sounds well! At the
                                        same time if he questiones himself closely, he will find,
                                        that he had the interest before all, to quench his interieur
                                        uneasiness, which he was sure, as he has found on former
                                        occasion, he would have felt and be troubled with, that
                                        would have cost him an hour and half's of sleep, or more,
                                        had he not given the shilling away——uneasiness resulted by
                                        means of a particular sentimental education, some others are
                                        fully free of. All may be reduced to interestedness, and I
                                        consider it mere proudness of one, to belive himself exempte
                                        of it. But I admit of a difference in the sort of
                                        interestedness. I find that the meanness of a man's
                                        interest, increases in direct ratio to the closeness it is
                                        stationed, to the hand of those that want to attain it. For
                                        example:——The prussian Hussars—those who give no pardon, but
                                        are always glad to take it— stand in the roaring battle. A
                                        lieutenant is taken prisoner, because his hors has kicked
                                        him off. The commanding general calls for volunteers to free
                                        him, of two drummers that hold him. As none comes out of the
                                        file he offers 15 jute Jroschen to bring him hither. A
                                        patriotic “Hinterpommer” spurs his fiery steed and fetches
                                        the swooming lieutenant back, tied to his horses tale … etc.
                                        The fellow may have had different interests for doing this
                                        heroic action. The nearest interest was the fifteen “jute
                                                Jros<ex>c</ex>hen”—the second: the leaden decoration
                                        his is sure to get, the third: the applause of the multitude
                                        together with the gentle stroke on his cheek by the
                                        astonished general, the fourth: that he will go to heaven
                                        for it and the fifth: that, should he ever get himself in
                                        trouble, by stealing a cotton pocket handkerchief of his
                                        corporal, he would have the probability, instead of being
                                        otherwise shot, to be pardoned to 150&#160;lashes only. You
                                        clearly see: the first interest— about the money—was the
                                        vilest; the following grew nobler and nobler … <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001027">Creamer</persName> and
                                                <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003494">Odgers</persName>, I believe had an interest, to be
                                        international, which was very close at hand: The applause of
                                        the multitude to which he belonged, and personal prospects.
                                        They care, <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">b<ex>e</ex>yond</expan> this a “damm” for their
                                        class. They were as good Englishmen as any
                                        bourg<ex>e</ex>ois, and thought little about continental
                                        affairs, which only may bear a very remote interest indeed.
                                        Up to now, I found the great heap of working men as
                                        creatures, that can no further be trusted, as the profit is
                                        within the reach of their mouth, and even then you want a
                                        deal of persuasion to make them bite. They fell off.—They
                                        will come to again, and—belive me—the same may fell off
                                        again. Never trust them far! I hate faithlessness more than
                                        death. In matters of importance one should never give his
                                        word, unless he feels himself man to fall with it. There are
                                        occasions in life, when we may—in the worst of cases—fail …
                                        where unlooked for circumstances laid rocks in our ways …
                                        There are others—we <hi rendition="#u">dare</hi> not fail,
                                        whatever unlooked for events will thunder down our might.
                                        Where I feel myself to weak—I never promise.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">I waited with this letter, as I thought
                                                <seg type="comment"><orig>your Hamburg
                                                  Kaufmann</orig><note xml:id="b87b2070-2c43-419f-a961-7aa77ae3b6f0"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000011173">Theodor
                                                  Heinrich Menke</persName>. Siehe auch <ref target="B00079">L. Kugelmann an Marx,
                                                  30.3.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170419T112944+0200" comment="{{Br. 76.7}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref>
                                                  und <ref target="B00086/#start_uwn_d15_4z">Marx an
                                                  L. Kugelmann,
                                                  6.4.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170419T113815+0200" comment="{{Br._83.17–23}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref>).</note></seg>,
                                        would make his apparition. Up to now, no such thing has
                                        called on me.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">I have seen your friend <seg type="comment"><orig>Chily</orig><note xml:id="de244892-1704-44c3-ae6a-96987e371429"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000004249">Victor
                                                  Schily</persName>. </note></seg>. He is well, and
                                        conveys his amities. He told me, that he had written a
                                        letter for you, but, it had been laying by for some time,
                                        and then, when he came to read it once again, he made <hi rend="background(yellow)">up</hi> his mind to write
                                        another. So it rested. He is not like I—I send them away
                                        whatever nonsense It will once contain. I know, friends will
                                        be indulgent. He promised to make up for his neglectfulness.
                                        He asked me, whether I kept <seg type="comment"><orig><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000317">Becker's</persName> monthly <bibl sameAs="zzDer Vorbote">journal</bibl>.</orig><note xml:id="f6defc61-bce7-4c4e-b3e4-c09dc674c021">„Der
                                                  Vorbote“ (Genf). (((zDer_Vorbote))) </note></seg>
                                        I had the misfortune of saying I found it to dry for my
                                        taste. He seemed much vexed about this, and meant; that
                                        since I am in the money making line, it is not surprising, I
                                        find all other things dry. He is agent for this our friend
                                                <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000317">Becker's</persName> journal. He is agent for a
                                        german “Unterstützungs-Verein” etc. We made the matter moist
                                        again, by some glasses of small beer. He is a right charming
                                        man, obligeing to everyone, only, as far as I can judge—but
                                        shallow in politics. </p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><pb/> III <pb/> The new invention, I had
                                        spoken to you about <seg type="comment"><orig>in my last
                                                  letter,</orig><note xml:id="fb24a354-0351-4b1e-84e4-61ac8eef8fe7">Siehe <ref target="B00069">K. Kaub an Familie
                                                  Marx
                                                  17.3.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170403T140731+0200" comment="{{Br. 65}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref>.</note></seg>
                                        is still a most mysterious affair. Baron <persName key="ed_kvh_jmc_3y">Gablenz</persName>, with whom we
                                        had chiefly to do in the matter, as he was told to have the
                                        “sack”, wanted a price to be made before hand, as he had
                                        already been taken in somewhere else, and when we told him,
                                        together with the conditio<hi rend="background(yellow)">n</hi>, that half the money should be paid at once,
                                        the other half, the day before the trial, as it is usual
                                        with all inventors—who never like else paying, should the
                                        invention proove bad—he found us to dear and to sharp for
                                        his sweet taste. He expected we wanted to work and be out of
                                        pocket <seg type="comment"><orig>“pour l'amour de ses beaux
                                                  yeux”</orig><note xml:id="dd030855-62c3-43f7-8ae1-6e33eb15e824">Nach
                                                  <persName key="ed_xmk_2kz_bz">La Grange</persName>
                                                  in <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000011201">Molières</persName> Komödie „Les Précieuses
                                                  ridicules“. Szene&#160;15: „Mais ils n’auront pas
                                                  l’avantage de se servir de nos habits pour vous
                                                  donner dans la vue; et si vous les voulez aimer,
                                                  ce sera, ma foi, pour leurs beaux yeux. Vîte,
                                                  qu’on les dépouille sur le champ.“
                                                  (((lMolière:_Les Précieuses ridicules)))
                                                </note></seg>—because we would have the honour to
                                        starve pour Monsieur le Baron … However it is quite likely
                                        we shall nevertheless get something to do with it, through
                                        some other of the noble protectors—who pay before hand
                                        naturally—and who are less miserly than Baron <persName key="ed_kvh_jmc_3y">Gablenz</persName>. Hang the
                                        fellow!</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Paris is putting on its sunday coat, and
                                        is beautifying in every corner for <seg type="comment"><orig>the coming exhibition, in 67.</orig><note xml:id="b66d2d0c-31b2-484b-8aa8-21c0e2ce8df8">Die
                                                  Weltausstellung 1867 in Paris.</note></seg> The
                                        building will be placed on the champ de Mars, of an oval
                                        construction and of stupefying demensions. If you should pay
                                        me a visit to Paris you will be surprised.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">We have had very hot weather already and
                                        a blue sky is more of a common think than in London. I think
                                        that ten years of blue sky are quite worth a lifetime of
                                        dull weather as you see in your quarter.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">My kind regards to M.&#160;<persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001603">Fox</persName>. He
                                        kept good—did not he?——T'is only pity he is so afraid to
                                        kill a king. We all have our weak places.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">W<ex>h</ex>y</expan> did
                                        you not tell me how <seg type="comment"><orig>your
                                                  work</orig><note xml:id="a4b78512-d849-4b84-a5fe-5e0cfa769880">Gemeint ist hier Karl Marx: Das Kapital; siehe
                                                  <ref target="B00007/#a85fd331-e369-4613-bae5-8b4731d7edc3">Erl. zu Marx an J. Ph. Becker, zwischen 9. und
                                                  15.1.1866. </ref><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170518T135337+0200" comment="{{Erl. 6b}}."?>
                                                  <?oxy_comment_end?>(((lMarx,Karl:DasKapital.Bd.1.Hamburg1867)))</note></seg>
                                        is progressing? Do you not like the tune?</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">My compliments to friend <persName key="ed_l54_cks_xy">Lessner</persName>—if you see
                                        him. He is as earnest a fellow as one to be found. I belive
                                        him to be the only one, of working men, that could be
                                        trusted to the fullest extend. There is no false string in
                                        him.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">My kindest love to all of you. I know
                                        Mohr has no time for writing such every day's talk as I do.
                                        I shall never trouble him. But good <seg type="comment"><orig>Jenny</orig><note xml:id="aa3f4e98-4fa5-4aff-aebb-e4fc7d4d22be"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003074">Jenny
                                                  Marx</persName> (Tochter). </note></seg> may do me
                                        the kindness, from time to time, if she happens to have an
                                        hour, that else would be lost to all, and write a word or
                                        two to one that holds you dear.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">How is my <seg type="comment"><orig>philosopher <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003076">Laura</persName>?</orig><note xml:id="f52db436-f4d6-4087-afec-c381744b689f"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003076">Laura
                                                  Marx</persName>. </note></seg> Still pensive? How
                                        l'ange bleue du Nord—little Thoussy. How your good <seg type="comment"><orig><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003075">mother</persName>.</orig><note xml:id="e93048d7-14d7-45b9-a03f-5108c1efd98b"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003075">Jenny
                                                  Marx</persName>. </note></seg> Did you have such
                                        good cake again as last year on Christmas? You remember, how
                                        I immolated myself in eating it—but it was stronger than I.
                                        What has become of <seg type="comment"><orig>Mistress'
                                                  Marx's <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000005086">brother</persName></orig><note xml:id="nnym_kqq_dz"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000005086">Edgar von
                                                  Westphalen</persName>.</note></seg>? The
                                        rattelsnake killer. I earnestly hope he aquired his health
                                        again.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">It says in <seg type="comment"><orig>a
                                                  very old song</orig><note xml:id="a23b0be7-fdad-4524-8569-b144df72feb4">Abgewandelter Text des deutschen Volksgesanges:
                                                  Je höher der Kirchturm desto schöner das Geläut,
                                                  je weiter mein Schätzel desto größer die
                                                  Freud.</note></seg> “Je höher die Glocken, je
                                        schöner's Geleut——Je weiter das Dirnderl, je größer die
                                        Freud'.“ It is a remarkable thing, that with the increase of
                                        distance, simular minds draw closer and closer. I remember,
                                        when I first left my fathers house, where I had passed a
                                        very dull youth, as dull as any boy may have passed one—it
                                        was perhaps the most happy hour of my life, when I saw the
                                        town vanish at a distance. I tell you: I was never so
                                        fortunate to know, what love to on's parents is. I hated my
                                                <persName key="ed_zw5_dtd_5z"><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>father<?oxy_custom_end?></persName>,
                                        I barely once knew my <persName key="ed_k2h_ctd_5z"><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>mother<?oxy_custom_end?></persName>
                                        and the world became my home. But a few miles distance, a
                                        few years time, soon mended all, and as misfortune had long
                                        created the simularity of mind in me and them—soon space
                                        between us, brought us closer to each oneother. We grew
                                        friends, and were no less sorry, for what has passed in
                                        younger days, when we had to part for ever. I remember I
                                        wept.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">It seems to me, that you, who had as
                                        well not always sun<hi rend="background(yellow)">s</hi>hine
                                        in your garden, are simular to me, however great a
                                        difference may be, in o<hi rend="background(yellow)">ur</hi>
                                        ways of walking through the mud. The little distance that
                                        came now between, makes me think we are old cousins and
                                        knew' anothers for theese twenty years.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">If you look at a fine country, from the
                                        hight of some mountain top, down at the distance in a
                                        peaceful vale—Your eye will grow voratious at the sight. Go
                                        down from your hill, look close at the play—see the cowdung
                                        in the roads, the roughness of the path, the sweating
                                        pasants, a heap of lousy children, a stinking pool before
                                        each peasant's house a drunken woman bowing to the cross—you
                                        will look back in full disgust and see the hill wherever you
                                        stood, as <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">be<ex>a</ex>utyful</expan> as you did see the
                                        dale before … I think there is no dale so deep, and no hill
                                        so high, we have more or less looked closely to. We need
                                        never fear to loose our humour at the sight. We will, I
                                        hope, be able to look ever from the longest distance at each
                                        other, however near we might yet be. Won't that be the
                                        style?——all right! Ich habe Durst bekommen über dem vielen
                                        Schreiben. Fare you well. Sonstige Neuigkeiten gibt's jetzt
                                        kaum u. die <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">meiste<ex>n</ex></expan> Sachen bleiben beim
                                        alten.</p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Grüße mir auch <seg type="comment"><orig><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001129">Kaetchen</persName>.</orig><note xml:id="c61b9dd9-2ce1-49b3-80c7-1974abf2f684">Vermutlich <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001129">Helena
                                                  Demuth</persName>. </note></seg></p>
                                <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Auf baldige Antwort hofft Euer
                                        Freund</p>
                                <closer sameAs="MBUnterschrift">Ch. Kaub </closer>
                        </div>
                </body>
        </text>
</TEI>