<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00147" xml:lang="de"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title><idno>143</idno>Karl Kaub an Karl Marx in London. Paris, Montag, 30. Juli 1866</title></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition ana="#firstEdition">Dieser Brief wird hier erstmals veröffentlicht.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><institution>IISG</institution><collection>Marx-Engels-Nachlass</collection><idno><idno type="shelfmark">D 2621/D V 46 Fotosign. 9578e.</idno></idno></msIdentifier><physDesc>
            <p>Der Brief besteht aus zwei Bogen dünnem, weißem Papier im Format 266&#160;×&#160;207
              bzw. 208&#160;mm. Die erste, dritte und fünfte Seite hat Kaub vollständig beschrieben,
              die siebente zu zwei Dritteln, die übrigen vier Seiten sind leer. Schreibmaterial:
              schwarze Tinte.</p>
            <p>Die Schreibweise wurde nicht berichtigt.</p>
            <p><ref target="mega_bzq_zdv_vy">Dem Brief liegt ein Zeitungsausschnitt bei.</ref></p>
            <p><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170424T151005+0200" comment="Die Beilage (Z. 103–104) siehe unten."?></p>
            <?oxy_comment_end?>
            <p><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170424T142858+0200" comment="{beilage}Wiedergabe der Beilage"?><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="207,241,255" mid="2"?></p>
            <?oxy_comment_end?>
            <p><?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170424T142348+0200" comment="alles bei der Beilage:
IISG, Marx-Engels-Nachlaß, Sign. D 1621/D V 46. Fotosign. 9578e.
Die Worte „beacoup“ und „bien compris.“ hat Kaub mit Tinte??? unterstrichen, hach dem Wort „enfants!“ ein Fragezeichen in Klammern gesetzt. [Gestaltung: MEGA² III/13. S. 1120]"?></p>
            <?oxy_comment_end?>
            <p/>
            <?oxy_custom_end mid="2"?>
          </physDesc><additional><listBibl><bibl>RGASPI f. 1 op. 5 d. 1669</bibl></listBibl></additional></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><correspDesc><correspAction type="sent"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460">Karl Kaub</persName><placeName>Paris</placeName><date when="1866-07-30"/></correspAction><correspAction type="received"><persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName><placeName>London</placeName></correspAction></correspDesc></profileDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2016-10-31T13:39:44Z</date> | <name>Regina Roth</name> | <orgName>Telota</orgName> | OxGarage DOCX to TEI | 2.15.0</change><change><date>2016-10-31T14:57:10+01:00</date> | <name>Sascha Grabsch</name> | <orgName>Telota</orgName> | convert_tei_file.py | 0.85</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="writingAct">
        <opener>
          <dateline sameAs="MBDatumszeile"><pb/> Paris le 30 Juillet/66</dateline>
          <salute sameAs="MBAnrede">My dear Marx,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p sameAs="MBAdresse">33, Rue des trois Couronnes, du Temple</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextohneEinzug">I hope you have received <seg type="comment"><orig>my last
              letter,</orig><note xml:id="fd2c9371-2185-49ac-a44e-0529ff951e87"><ref target="B00101">Karl Kaub an Familie Marx ,
                1.5.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170405T190739+0200" comment="{Br. 97}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?></ref></note></seg>
          which, as much as I remember, will not have failed to charm you, for the amount of
          nonsense developed in it. Sense is so rare in our age, and one does always well, to do
          like the majority does.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Unfortunately I have much lazy time now, and I earnestly regret,
          that none of my London friends come to pay me a visit. I could have been on the spree with
          him all day and night. Since <seg type="comment"><orig>this nice war</orig><note xml:id="b2e1cac5-d099-4a8b-9079-aefd757a0a53">Der Deutsche Krieg (1866).</note></seg>
          broke out, things broke down altogether in France and especially in Paris. We for our
          part, we have absolutely nothing to do, and intend to shut shop completely this week. As
          for being paid, for work that has been done, before this crisis, it is utterly impossible.
          We were often, theese last days, in a most awkward position, as we work only for one
          customer almost, and the fellow not giving us a farthing, although he oughs us some
          16&#160;000&#160;Francs now. We had bills to meet of a large amount, and no probability of
          doing so. One time we were even much afraid, we should never get paid, as the man had some
          heavy losses to encounter. We got over it, but I assure you, not without great pains. On
          the whole, I found Frenchmen to be as big thiefes as the rest of mankind. They bear it
          very openly too, and the English proverbe: “rather be a thief than a fool” can not be of
          other than of french origin. You have no idea with which naivete a French Bourgeois is
          capable to say: he knows he is a rogue, but that you can't hurt him. Had I known what I
          know now, I should never have taken my bones to fair France. If I was sure, I could do
          without brains, I would have tried to blow the little I have even out. As poeple told me
          lately, that it was very unhealthy to do so, I decided to leave them in, for the
          present.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">There are some poeple, doing very well here in Paris. <hi rend="background(yellow)">These</hi> are the “Prussians“. Since the break out <hi rend="background(yellow)">of this</hi> war, the german brewers, that done very badly all
          the beginning of the summer, on account of the Cholera, can not now brew enough, and the
          rooms are daily crowded.—</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">“Kannegießen” the exclusively german speciality, the only thing
          in which they really excell, is there blooming in its smartest colours. They are so happy
          at it, that it would be pity, to see them disturbed. <pb/> I firstly was thoroughly
          disgusted with it, but when I one eavening saw, how one broad shoulderd Knödelfresser,
          turned out three proud children of Berlin, two of which were exmembers of <seg type="comment"><orig>the celebrated National-Verein</orig><note xml:id="nrg4_lhs_gz">Der
              Deutsche Nationalverein (1859-1867).</note></seg>—happy remembrance!—I got reconciled
          at this outbreak of German energy, and went often then, to amuse myself with similar
          scenes. Poor National-Verein&#160;… they can no more talk now of “Bürgerwehr und
            Volksbewaffnung”—<seg type="comment"><orig><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000005131">The
                gallant king of Prrrrrr&#160;…</persName>
            </orig><note xml:id="nig3_yhs_gz"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000005131">Wilhelm
                I.</persName>
            </note></seg>has armed them—and they do well. <seg type="comment"><orig>The
              Bavarian</orig><note xml:id="f48ba8c1-a1c4-40aa-80e3-35217904d519"><persName key="ed_mjd_1xs_gz">Ludwig&#160;II.</persName>
            </note></seg> had said: that never kings ridiculised themselves more, throughout all
          German history, than they had done of late. The crowned king of Prr—he said—who is the
          most monstrous representative of feudalisme in Europe and who has set out a general day of
          penitence and prayer throughout his happy lands—makes evolution now, and deals in freeing
          countries from the foreign yoke! <seg type="comment"><orig>His apostolic
              majesty</orig><note xml:id="nt2f_33s_gz"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003745">Pius
                IX.</persName>
            </note></seg> prostituting himself at the feet of <seg type="comment"><orig>the hero of
              December,</orig><note xml:id="ebf70253-0f68-4658-b96c-ea8ba8f2b040"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000003392">Napoléon III</persName> – er hatte am 2._Dezember 1851
              einen Staatsstreich durchgeführt und wurde am 2._Dezember 1852 zum Kaiser der
              Franzosen ausgerufen. </note></seg> by laying his future in his hands. The two
          Berliner Kinder, who by the by, found it safer to stay here in Paris, then to fight “pour
          le roi de Prusse”—spoke much of prussian courage, of <seg type="comment"><orig>the great
              Frederic,</orig><note xml:id="nky4_q3s_gz"><persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000010589">Friedrich II.</persName>
            </note></seg>
          <seg type="comment"><orig>of 13, 14, 15,</orig><note xml:id="cf3de0fd-d354-47d2-a0dc-ee1e86718c4c">Anspielung auf die Teilnahme Preußens am
              Kampf gegen das napoleonische Frankreich in den Jahren1813–1815.</note></seg> of their
          giving no pardon, but beeing always ready to take it and of their beeing the first nation
          on the face of earth. They came from words to blows and out went the manly
          prussians&#160;… I loose all hope—but the right of the strongest will still be the final
          solution of all questiones, from Berlin on the sand, up to Paris on the Seine!</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">The only consolation in this whole affaire I can get is, that
          Germany has, besides of a sentimental viewing at the question, very little or nothing to
          loose in this ridiculous struggle and any future struggle or quarrel that may ensue:
          Politically—in its earliest childhood, not even capable of keeping its linen
          dry—socially—not at all existing, morally a spiteful sentimental set of dreamers,
          physically such as can be: an almost exclusively potato eating population—abstraction made
          of a few, that feed on salt herrings, on the borders of the Spree<hi rend="background(yellow)">..</hi>—geographically: a mere denomination—nationally: mere
          Franzosenfressers, which they unfortunately digest to russian excrements etc. etc. such as
          they were, I say, they can not loose. Not, like in <seg type="comment"><orig>the memorable
              anti slavery war,</orig><note xml:id="nmcq_n4s_gz">Der Amerikanische Bürgerkrieg
              (1861–1865).</note></seg> where there was a sharpely defined social development
          suffocated, in its early youth, together with the reptile that tried to suck its very life
          out, not like in America, where a social existence has existed and in consequence, there
          could be a danger of loosing by waring—there can nothing of the sort be lost in our rotten
          Fatherland.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">The American war has done harm to the whole world, has weeled
          back history of 50&#160;years, has cheated mankind out of its best hopes and hard work.
          Germany by waring will cheat nobody—but himself, by revolutionising with their sovereigns
          at their heads. </p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><pb/> I heard of good sources, that there was a new invention
          made in France—<hi rendition="#u">a new canon</hi>, that shall lick all that has been got
          up to now. Some 80 of them were tried, found good<hi rend="background(yellow)">,</hi> and
          packed up in large strong packing cases, with the governements seal put on them, ready to
          be remooved, in time of need, from this place of confinement, on to the layers of the
          former guns. Should they be meant to accompany the psalm of 13, 14, 15?</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><seg type="comment"><orig>Some days ago I read in the <bibl sameAs="zzThe Times">Times</bibl>, that she felt “unutterably” released at the news
              of the probability of a peace being concluded</orig><note xml:id="ngl2_2js_gz">Vermutlich meint <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460">Kaub</persName> einen dieser
              beiden Beiträge: The Negotiations. In: The Times. London. Nr. 25_560, 26. Juli 1866.
              S. 5; The prolongation of the armistice … [Leitart.] In: The Times. London. Nr.
              25_562, 28. Juli 1866. S. 8. (((lThe Negotiations. In: The Times. London. Nr. 25_560,
              26. Juli 1866. S. 5))) (((lThe prolongation of the armistice … [Leitart.] In: The
              Times. London. Nr. 25_562, 28. Juli 1866. S. 8)))</note></seg> If this shuffle had
          lasted another few weeks, it is not unlikely, that English working classes might have been
          able to get part of what they worked so long and tenously for. As it were—I fear they will
          meet with little sucsess. However English perseverance is mightier than French outbursts
          of anger—and what remains unfinished now, may be completed in a six month, when they will
          begin to fight on the Continent again. I do not belive in peace. Prussian politic has
          created a deep hatered among the individuals even.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">The French press is doing a great deal now in political economy.
          Almost every paper brings dayly arguments to proove the working classes, that they can all
          do very well if they only live economically: that means to say: work much and consume
          little. <seg type="comment"><orig>The <bibl sameAs="zzLe Moniteur universel du soir">Moniteur</bibl> as well has those last weeks brought a serie of articles called:
              the ABC of travailleurs.</orig><note xml:id="nwvf_lks_gz">Siehe Le Moniteur du soir
              commencera dans son numéro du 16_mai, sous le titre: ABC du travailleurs. In: Le
              Moniteur universel. Paris. Nr._135, 15._Mai 1866. S._578; weitere Angaben waren nicht
              zu ermitteln. (((lLe Moniteur du soir commencera ... In: Le Moniteur universel. Paris.
              Nr._ 135, 15._Mai 1866. S._578/unter M einstellen)))</note></seg> The amount of
          ridiculous platitudes that are exhibited are most amusing. <seg type="comment"><orig>In
              another serie they gave the life of <persName key="ed_q2c_zqk_sy"><hi rendition="#u">Jaquart</hi></persName>,</orig><note xml:id="nibj_4ms_gz">Hierzu konnten keine
              Daten ermittelt werden.</note></seg> the inventor of weaving machines called the
          “métier Jaquart.” Same arguments—same voidness of sense. In England such thrash would
          become impossible. Every school boy would be able to contradict them. Even the illustrated
          papers bring outlines of this kind and <seg type="comment"><orig>I have cut a few lines
              out yesterday, which I inclose.</orig><note xml:id="d834185a-458a-48fe-9e1a-58b989c735d4">Siehe die <ref target="mega_bzq_zdv_vy">Wiedergabe der Beilage</ref>.</note></seg> The middle class must be aware of the
          bad cause they work for, because they excuse themselves so often, while no devil accuses
          them. If they had some sense, they would say nothing at all.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><seg type="comment"><orig>Bürger Weber</orig><note xml:id="no34_3ns_gz">Vermutlich <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000005033">Joseph
                Valentin Weber</persName>. </note></seg> has been here, and had, as much as I have
          been told, kicked up such an awful row, at “Kannegießing” in a brassserie dans la rûe
          Blondel, that poeple stopped in the street. He offerd to hid a young man of 20&#160;years
          of age for his opinion, and to kick him out at the doors. He has done nothing of the sort
          in reality you may imagine. It was only an outburst of long retained Bierhaus-Politik and
          the poor young chap had to stand to it. I have no doubt but what his health must have
          improoved after such a spree. I have not seen him. I think or rather was told, that he
          made an invention, which he expected to be able to sell over here. </p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug"><pb/> How are you getting on with <seg type="comment"><orig>your
              Economy?</orig><note xml:id="bf84de9d-13c6-4ee0-a573-7c89ebb44783">Gemeint ist hier
              Karl Marx: Das Kapital; siehe <ref target="B00007/#a85fd331-e369-4613-bae5-8b4731d7edc3">Erl. zu Marx an J. Ph. Becker,
                zwischen 9. und
                15.1.<?oxy_comment_start author="reichhoff" timestamp="20170516T135827+0200" comment="{{Erl. 6b}}"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?>.</ref>
              (((lMarx,Karl:DasKapital.Bd.1.Hamburg1867)))</note></seg> I wish most earnestly to see
          it completed. There is no sience more wrapt up in darkness than this, <expan resp="editor" sameAs="dottet_underline">an<ex>d</ex></expan> no darkness more wanted to be swept away
          than that on political economy. It is very interesting to know whether there is an
          atmosphere round the moon and whether the white spots on heaven are stars or not; but it
          is uncalcula<hi rend="background(yellow)">b</hi>ly more needful to know whether our
          present system is a necessary and an eternal one or not. With all the knowledge of the
          moon, poeple will still live miserable and die before their time—with the knowledge of the
          other they will become able to alter all. Let me know something about it. Do—there is a
          good boy! How is your health going on. A few weeks of Paris would have done you a deel of
          good. <seg type="comment"><orig>I hope you had not the same unfortunate summer to pass as
              last year.</orig><note xml:id="a9ccda08-6436-438a-8b91-0f3c50913af9">Wahrscheinlich
              erinnert <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002460">Kaub</persName> hier an Marx‘
              schlechten Gesundheitszustand und seine bedrückende finanzielle Situation im Sommer
              1865. Siehe MEGA²&#160;III/13. Br.&#160;265, Br._282, Br._288 und
            Br._292).</note></seg> Theese damned sicknesses have undoubtedly mostly prevented you
          from going a head. I many times thought of you and feared of an other treat of the
          kind.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Be so kind to remember me to your dear family, and tell them
          that they still enter for my dearest, of my remembrances.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">You will excuse me that I write in English, but it serves me at
            <hi rend="background(yellow)">the same</hi> time, as I chatt with my friends of old, as
          a lesson of repetition, and awakes a recollection of many things, that pleased me much and
          which I will never see no more. Sans caprices&#160;– pas d'existence! When you see
            <persName key="ed_l54_cks_xy">Lessner</persName> tell him that I have not forgotten him,
          and that I will write to him ere long.</p>
        <p sameAs="MBTextmitEinzug">Salut to <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000001603">Mr.
            Fox</persName>.</p>
        <closer sameAs="MBUnterschrift">I remain yours most affectionately<lb/>Ch. Kaub. </closer>
      </div></body></text></TEI>