<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="mega_b5c_qwz_sy">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ernest Jones an Edmond Beales, 31. Mai
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170203T160108+0100" comment="nochmal mit der Hs. verglichen, Seitenwechsel eingefügt - Ok"?>1866<?oxy_comment_end?>
                </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften (BBAW)</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc rend="manuscript">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>RGASPI</institution>
                        <idno><idno type="shelfmark">f. 1 op. 5 d. 1659</idno></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc>
                        <p>Kopie des Briefes von Ernest Jones an Edmond Beales vom 31. Mai 1866.</p>
                        <p>Archivsignatur des Moskauer Marx-Engels-Instituts (IMĖ): „Rj 1577d“ bzw.
                            „Rj 1576e“.</p>
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000002387">Jones, Ernest</persName>
                    <date when="1866-05-31" cert="high"/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName key="pdrPo.001.004.000000296">Beales, Edmond</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div type="writingSession">
                <opener>
                    <dateline><pb n=""/> Copy</dateline>
                    <dateline> 47, Princess St<hi rendition="#sup">r</hi> Manchester </dateline>
                    <dateline><hi rendition="#u">May 31. 1866</hi></dateline>
                    <salute>D<hi rendition="#sup">r</hi> Sir, </salute>
                </opener>
				<p>Do not let us drift into a <hi rendition="#u">personal difference</hi>. You greatly
                    misinterpret my letter if you suppose that I attribute to <hi rendition="#u">you
                        all</hi> the evil resulting from the policy adopted by the Executive of the
                    Reform League.</p>
                <p>What I wrote was this:</p>
                <p><?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>“<?oxy_custom_end?>You
                    say that <hi rendition="#u">your</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#u">entire</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#u">Council</hi>, with three exceptions supports the Bill. You
                    add that, at the Meetings called by you, &amp; by the Branches of the League
                    formed &amp; I may <hi rendition="#u">say</hi> inspired by your <hi rendition="#u">Coun<hi rendition="#uu">ci</hi>l<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?></hi>”<?oxy_custom_end?>
                        [[mark—Coun<hi rendition="#uu">ci</hi>l not Coun<hi rendition="#uu">se</hi>l]]
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="lindenberg" timestamp="20170203T142449+0100" comment="Anführungszeichen fehlt in Hs. --&gt; so übernommen"?>the<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    policy of supporting the Governm<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi> Bill is strongly
                    endorsed &amp; that <hi rendition="#uu">your</hi>
                    <hi rendition="#uu">League</hi> might become a nullity were you to oppose
                    it.<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>”<?oxy_custom_end?>
                </p>
                <p>You will therefore perceive that the “you” &amp; “your” applied to your
                    Committee, your <hi rendition="#u"><hi rendition="#uu">Council</hi></hi>, your
                    entire official organisation &amp; <hi rendition="#u">not to yourself alone
                        personally</hi>. <hi rendition="#u">But I cannot withdraw from you
                        personally, your proportionate share in the observation generally applied in
                        my former letter</hi>.</p>
                <p> You say you advocated Manhood suffrage at the interview with Lord Russel &amp;
                    at divers Meetings &amp; Conferences. Of course, you did! Who ever denied it!
                    Not I! You would not otherwise have been elected President of the Reform League
                    or, having been elected, retained your office.</p>
                <p>But this only renders the course pursued by you, <hi rendition="#u">&amp; your
                        colleagues</hi>, more to be lamented. For a Whig or a sham Liberal <hi rendition="#u">or even a Tory</hi> to recommend the People to support the
                        Governm<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi> Bill, I can readily understand &amp; such
                        recommendat<hi rendition="#sup">n</hi> from such quarters would be ——
                    comparatively harmless! <hi rendition="#u">But for, the President of a Manhood
                        Suffrage Association</hi> to support a Bill such as that issuing from the
                        Governm<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi>, is suicidal, &amp;, forgive the word,
                    politically criminal, however sincere &amp;
                    good<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>”<?oxy_custom_end?>
                    (as doubtlessly it was in your case) the original motive may have been that led
                    to such a fearful error.</p>
                <p>Of course, you at the same time advocate Manhood Suffrage—of course you tell the
                    Members of your League, that you will still agitate for Manhood Suffrage, &amp;
                    that the Governm<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi> Bill is not to be taken as a final
                    Measure<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>”<?oxy_custom_end?>
                    of course you do! you could do nothing less. But that just makes the poison more
                    dangerous, <pb n=""/> which you administer when you add:
                        <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>“<hi rendition="#u"><?oxy_custom_end?>Support the Bill</hi>—it is good as far as
                    it goes—it is a step in the right direction &amp; will lead to
                    more<?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>”<?oxy_custom_end?>,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>That the people are <hi rendition="#u">not</hi> with you, that you have no sway
                    over, no hold on, the healthy upright common sense of the Workingmen of London,
                    the signal failure on Primrose Hill sufficiently indicates. </p>
                <p>By that failure you have done a great injury to the cause of Manhood Suffrage;
                    for its enemies will construe the non attendance of the Workingmen on WhitMonday
                    into evidence of apathy as regards <hi rendition="#uu">all</hi> Reform—Whereas
                    in truth it merely shews their repudiation of the Policy you so strongly
                    advocate in your letter to me. That repudiation is further evidenced in the
                    constantly increasing number of letters I have been receiving ever since a few
                    lines from me on the suicidal policy of supporting the Governm<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi> Bill appeared in the three Manchester Papers. I
                    mention this merely to shew you that you are much in error as to the feelings of
                    the Working Classes on the subject.</p>
                <p>I trust nothing I have said in this or any other letter, may prove personally
                    offensive to yourself or any Gent<hi rendition="#sup">n</hi> connected with the
                    League. I do not intend that it should be so. Do not let it produce any ill
                    feeling between us. <hi rendition="#u">Let us remain friends</hi>. I hope we
                    shall yet be able to work together for <hi rendition="#u">Manhood Suffrage</hi>,
                    when the present hallucination has passed. Let us then try to repair the evil
                    that has been done, without recrimination and without any bitterness of
                    feeling.</p>
                <p>As this correspondence was public from its commencem<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi>
                    and your first letter was sent, as was my reply, thro’ the Secretary of the
                    League, I conclude the public nature of the said correspondence still continues,
                    &amp; send this thro’ the same channel, requesting you to lay the entire
                    correspondence before the Council. I am </p>
				<closer>
                    <salute>Dear Sir <lb/>Faithfully yours <lb/></salute>
                    <signed>Ernest Jones <lb/></signed>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Edmond Beales Esq<hi rendition="#sup">re</hi>
                        </addrLine>
                    </address>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>